how to deal with the po file
you can open the po file by 2 programs: wordpad and poedit 
but in nvda translation we use poedit  program
when we open the po file, we find a list of the messages. each mesage has its translation beside. if there is an untranslated message, just highlite it and press tab to go to the edit translation field
if you want to copy the original message and put it in the translation field, just press alt plus C. this happens when we find a name for a braille display machine for example. 
please note that the untranslated messages are located at the top of the file
the fuzzy messages are those which the machine translated them automatically if there's a translated message similar to it, so you should check it to see if it is translated correctly. if it is not, then you should retranslate it. if you aren't sure of the message translation, highlite the message and press alt plus E to open the edit menu then down arrow till you find the item "translation is fuzzy". after you finish translating the new messages, the message will go to its place.
note, the first message in the po file is  "secure desk top", so any message before it is untranslated or fuzzy
if the message is large, then you should open the file with wordpad to be able to read it completely.
in jaws you can use the following key commands:
- insert plus 1 to read the original message
- insert plus 2 to read the message translation
please note that you may find problems to read the arabic translation with jaws, in this case, you should use nvda. it works very well. you can read by character, word, or line using the arrow keys
if you want to test the translation you made copy the mo file that's created automatically and go to the following path: 
C:\Program Files\NVDA\locale\ar_sa\LC_MESSAGES and replace the mo file with the new one